<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A collection of divers papers presented unto the Houses of Parliament by the Commissioners of Scotland since May last, 1645.</title>
            <author>Scotland. Parliament.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1645</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 71 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A80106</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C5144</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E305_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200320</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861123</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861123</idno>
            <idno type="VID">113251</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A80106)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 113251)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 50:E305[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A collection of divers papers presented unto the Houses of Parliament by the Commissioners of Scotland since May last, 1645.</title>
                  <author>Scotland. Parliament.</author>
                  <author>Buchanan, David, 1595?-1652?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 31, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Moses Bell.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1645.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Published by authority."</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Octob. 15th";in imprint after London:"for Rob: Bostock"; at head of page [1]: "This preface forbidden by ye Scots Commissioners"; at foot of page [8]: "This preface written by David Buchanan".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Scotland --  History --  Charles I, 1625-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Corinne Vieracker</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Corinne Vieracker</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:113251:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:113251:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A COLLECTION Of divers Papers Preſented unto the Houſes of Parliament By the Commiſſioners of SCOTLAND ſince May laſt, 1645.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed by Authority.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>Moſes Bell.</hi> 1645.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:113251:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:113251:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Ingenuous and Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ere I preſent unto thee a Collection of ſome Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, of which I ſhall onely ſay that in them thou wilt finde Reaſon and Truth, the publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing whereof I am perſwaded in the firſt place will give content to men of judgement and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity, concerning divers things murmured and rumored every where almoſt againſt men ſo well deſerving in the ſervice of this Cauſe of God, and of his people, and conſequently a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Cauſe it ſelfe, for which they have, and doe undergoe ſo much hardſhip, toyling care, and hazard, &amp;c. in all theſe three King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes; not only in oppoſing the violence and plots of the open and declared enemy, but alſo in declining and ſtopping the undermining devices of counterfeit friends, and falſe brethren. In the next place it will make falſe-hearted and by-ended men bluſh for ſhame if they have any, as alſo the ſimpler ones acknowledge their owne ſillyneſſe, ſuffering themſelves thus to be deluded, and as it were led by the Noſe, by the ſpecious lyes of crafty and deceitfull men; but before thou goe to the reading of the papers themſelves, give me leave to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine thee a little with theſe enſuing lines: Of late many reproaches have been caſt upon the <hi>Scots,</hi> in the purſuance of the ſervice in this common Cauſe, namely for three things. Firſt, on the one ſide the Malignants, that is, the enemies of Church and State, adverſaries to our ſolemne Covenant blame the <hi>Scots,</hi> for preſſing and urging the
<pb facs="tcp:113251:3"/> ſetling of the Church-Government, to the end that all groſſe Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry and Superſtition, with Tyrannie may be pulled downe; as alſo all fanaticall errours and Hereſies, with confuſion may be repreſſed in the Church, and it preſerved pure as the Spouſe of Chriſt, according to his holy Word, and conforme to the practice of the firſt times, and example of the beſt reformed Neighbour Churches, as we are all bound by our ſolemne Oath; on the other ſide divers men of zeale, to the glory of God, and good of his people, blame the <hi>Scots,</hi> that they are too white-lipp'd, and doe not put home with vigour enough the ſetling of the Church, as they are conceived to have done in their owne Country, and ſo they are wiſh'd by theſe Zelots to make their ſtoutneſſe more clearely appeare in this buſineſſe of the Church, for theſe well-meaning men are grieved from their heart to ſee the ſetling of the Church, theſe five yeares in hand ſo ſlackly pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued; yea in the latter times, ſtopped by ſome of thoſe who formerly did make a ſhew of an earneſt affection for the ſetling of the ſame as aforeſaid; but now with an unparallel'd impudency doe publickly affirme, that Religion was not the firſt and maine quarrell betwixt the Parliament and the common enemy, againſt the Declaration of both Houſes when they tooke Armes, and againſt the Declaration of both Kingdomes joyntly, and more particularly againſt the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall Covenant. To this it is anſwered; the <hi>Scots</hi> in conſcience and duty to God and his people, and particularly by ſolemne Oath are bound to put on the ſetling of the Church with all faithfulneſſe and earneſtneſſe, and yet they have to this day proceeded therein with all meekeneſſe, longanimity and tenderneſſe, ſtudying to gaine by faire meanes thoſe who are ſo backward to the ſetling of the Church if it were poſſible.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>Scots</hi> on one ſide are blamed by thoſe who are enemies to the ſetling of Government in the Church, and good order in the State, for expreſſing ſo ſeriouſly their deſires of peace, the Church being ſetled in truth and purity, and the State ſecured, with due Priviledges and lawfull liberty. And on the other ſide, divers blame the <hi>Scots</hi> for not preſſing home enough the obtaining of Peace, ſo much the rather that they are affraid to have a Peace, both long in comming and uncertain when it is come, except the <hi>Scots</hi> preſſe it, and be engaged in it. To this it is likewiſe anſwered; the <hi>Scots</hi> have undertaken war, not to make a Trade of it, but to obtaine peace, and the ſconer the better
<pb facs="tcp:113251:3"/> for the ſtopping of the torrent of wickedneſſes of all kinds ſo openly, and with ſo high a hand committed againſt God, and the wrongs done unto his people in warre; for they finde by woefull experience that the Sword is the heavieſt of the three maine ſcourges wherewith God puniſheth the children of men for their iniquities; yet they conceive the thing is to be done with judgement and diſcretion, for fear of ſurpriſall, and circumvention by the common enemy, who ſtudieth to undoe us by deceit, in making an uncertaine peace (if not preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by wiſedome) ſince he failes in his plots and open violence by warre to deſtroy us.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The <hi>Scots</hi> are blamed that their Army hath done nothing this Summer, and hath laine heavily upon the people, yea, and put Taxes upon them, to a huge and immence value if it went through the whole Country. To this alſo it is anſwered; If the <hi>Scots</hi> have done nothing, I pray you where doth the fault lye, for they have been ever willing and ready; with us when we will have the Plough to goe, firſt we give meate both to man and beaſt; next we furniſh the Plough with all inſtruments, as ſock, culter, &amp;c. fit for the worke: then let it be knowne with what and in what meaſure the <hi>Scots</hi> have been furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed for any undertaking, yea, in downe-right tearmes, they have been ſo dealt withall, that it ſeemeth there hath been a ſet deſigne to keepe them from doing, and to make them odious to the people; yet they have not been idle notwithſtanding their wants, for the ſending of the King twice South-ward, and the breaking his Northerne deſign is as advantagious to the main ſervice of the common Cauſe as any thing hath been done any where this yeare; all wiſe and judicious men doe acknowledge and confeſſe this. To lay aſide divers other particulars done by the <hi>Scots</hi> this yeare, but as for the Taxes or Aſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, ſaid to be againſt the liberty of the people, it is anſwered; that firſt they are moderate, and reach no further then the places neareſt unto their quarters, not going through the whole Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, as ſome doe ſeeme to intimate in their letters; then if it be againſt the liberty of the people without Ordinance from Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to lay Aſſeſments upon the Country, it is againſt the nature of men to live upon nothing, or ſtarve till Order from Authority come. Againe, I pray you whether or not is it more convenient for the people that moderate Aſſeſments ſhould be laid upon them, then that the Souldier driven by neceſſity ſhould take at diſcretion. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb facs="tcp:113251:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> whether or not is it better for keeping an Army of foot for the good of the people to have a ſet Taxe paid and appointed in a place, then to run up and downe at all times for proviſions; are not the forces in the Weſt driven to the ſame exigencies for want of pay? yea, ſome of late although they have been formerly with care lookt unto, have abandoned their Colours and run away: yet I am ſure if the <hi>Scots</hi> Army had the fourth part of pay that the Weſterne hath had this Summer, they would render ten for one for any thing that ſhould be taken from the people, of this they have given evidence enough by their former carriage in this Kingdome: moreover, they have frequently and earneſtly ſolicited for pay to fit them for action, and keepe them from being troubleſome to the people; and ſince they ſpeake of liberty, I pray you if the <hi>Scots</hi> had not come in where had the liberty been, and where had the Parliament been ſiting for judgeing of the liberty of the people? Is it not knowne to all that the Parliament is Aſſembled at the occaſion of the in-coming of the <hi>Scots,</hi> then the Court Plots againſt the Parliament were diſappointed by reaſon of the being of the <hi>Scots</hi> Army in <hi>England</hi> Thirdly, the <hi>Scots</hi> being ſolicited by the Court upon great promiſes to ſide with it againſt the Parliament, not onely refuſed to doe it as moſt baſe, but alſo gave notice of it to the Parliament with aſſuranee of their ſervice. Laſtly, if the <hi>Scots</hi> had not come in when they came, where had the liberty of the Parliament and people been ere now. After all this, ſome malicious men ſtudying to advance their worldly condition and private ends, by confuſion in the Church, and diſorder in the State, doe what they can to give a diſtaſte to Parliament, City, and Country of the <hi>Scots,</hi> but in vaine, for as ſure as the malicious calumnies of Papiſts, and Prelates, with their adherents hath come to nothing, and their devices fallen upon their owne heads; ſo without doubt ere it be long theſe enemies to the ſetling of the Church of God with their wickedneſſe and pride, will fall to the ground notwithſtanding all their cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and craft, for nothing can ſubſiſt but truth and honeſty.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:113251:4"/>
            <head>A Collection of divers Papers given in to the two Houſes of Parliament by the Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners of Scotland.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He ſenſe of the goodneſſe of God in the late vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory granted to the Forces of the Parliament, the experience of all ages wherein the greateſt and moſt ſudden victories, have through ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty or negligence ſo far miſcarried, that they have proved either hurtfull or unprofitable; and the deſires we have that this preſent victory may be thankfully and wiſely im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved to the honour of God and the publike good; have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained us humbly to offer our thoughts and deſires about this matter of ſo great weight and conſequence, that by this hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Committee they may be repreſented to the honourable Houſes of <hi>Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt we deſire, that unto the publike and ſolemn thanks gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving already offered unto God, there may ſucceed a publike and reall teſtimony of thankfulneſſe in the ſpeedy ſetling of Religion and the Houſe of God, wherein his glory and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour is neerely concerned; no monument or Trophee of vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory can be ſo pleaſant in his ſight; nothing will more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme and incourage all good Chriſtians at home, and comfort and ſatisfie all the Proteſtant Churches abroad; no means will be more effectuall for ſetling of unſtable minds, for curing and
<pb facs="tcp:113251:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:113251:5"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:113251:6"/> preventing of Sects, Schiſmes and Hereſ es, and for ſtopping the mouthes, and ſhaming the faces of ſuch as have not been aſhamed to ſay; That the Parliament in policy pretendeth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, but doth not really intend it, and thereby draw many Diſciples after them.</p>
            <p>Secondly, leaſt victories run continually in a viciſſitude, as they have at ſome times done formerly, which is not onely a ſigne but a means of the continuance of this unnaturall warre; we deſire that preſently, while the iron is hot, and before the Enemy gather ſtrength againe, courſe may be taken by the joint Councels and forces of both Kingdomes, for the ſpeeedy vigorous and conſtant proſecuting of the war, that by the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of God it may at laſt be brought to an end, and nothing may be left undone which may be a meanes to deliver theſe Kingdomes from their preſent ſad condition, under the heavy hand of God.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, we humbly move and deſire it may be conſidered, whether the preſent condition of the Kings Army, and the bleſſing of God upon the Parliaments forces, both of them joyned, make not an opportunity and ſuch a ſeaſon as is very deſirable for renewing the deſires of the Parliaments of both Kingdomes, in the moſt convenient and conduceable way for a juſt and well grounded Peace. Thus apprehending all occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of demanding Peace, it will appeare, that although War be neceſſarily in our hand, yet Peace is in our heart, and that we follow not War as a trade, or for it ſelfe, but as a means of Peace. If it ſhall pleaſe God to move the Kings heart to liſten unto our juſt and neceſſary deſires, our troubles are at an end, and we may ſit downe in peace: But if God ſhall ſo far deſert the King, that he will ſtill prefer the pernitious and deſtructive ſuggeſtions of wicked men, unto the Counſels of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of both Kingdoms; In that caſe we may ſay before God, our owne conſciences and the world, that we have delivered our owne ſouls, our Enemies will be convinced that peace is
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:113251:6"/> our deſires, our friends will extend themſelves to the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of a neceſſary war, and the Armies of both Kingdomes will doe duty with the greater reſolution and courage, when they ſee no other remedy, which may be a means upon this ſide to bring the war to a ſpeedy and happy concluſion.</p>
            <p>Theſe our motions &amp; deſires, we humbly preſent to be ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly conſidered by the wiſdome of the honourable Houſes, that the Lord Chancellor of <hi>Scotland,</hi> being now about his journey into that Kingdome, may be acquainted with their reſolutions, and may make the ſame knowne unto the Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh Army in this Kingdome, and to the Parliament of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> that all matters, whether of Peace or Warre, may ſtill proceed with the conſent of both Kingdomes.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>20 <hi>June,</hi> 1645.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>By command of the Commiſſioners for the Parliament of</hi> Scotland. John Cheiſley.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <p>HAving now ſeen and peruſed the divers Letters and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers of great importance, mentioned in the Anſwer of the honourable Houſes of Parliament, to our paper of the twentieth of <hi>June,</hi> which may give light to the future proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of both Kingdoms, having alſo obſerved the good ſucceſſe of the Parliaments Forces ſince that time, whereby the King and his Armies are brought to a much lower condition, which in Divine Providence may be a further preparation to an hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Peace; and having reaſon from what we have learned in time paſt, to apprehend, that men will not be at reſt, but ſtill be dealing under hand, and tampering for a Peace of their own making, and for their owne private ends, to the great preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice of the Publike, the further alienating of the Kings heart from a ſafe and well grounded Peace, and the delaying of the intentions of both Kingdomes; We do in all earneſtneſſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:113251:7"/> upon the grounds and conſiderations preſented in our former paper, to know rhe minde and reſolution of both Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes in a matter of ſo great conſequence, as is the renewing of the deſires and propoſitions of Peace, (in ſuch wanner as ſhall be thought fit,) that we may make the ſame knowne to the Parliament of <hi>Scotland</hi> now ſitting, which may expect no leſſe from our truſt and diligence.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>28 <hi>July,</hi> 1645.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>By command of the Commiſſioners for the Parliament of</hi> Scotland. John Cheiſley.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <p>THe preſſing neceſſities of the Scottiſh Army doe inforce us to repreſent by your Lordſhips and theſe Gentlemen, to the honourable Houſes of Parliament, that notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the whole foure moneths of the Ordinance be long ſince expired, there is but a very ſmall and inconſiderable proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of money aſſeſſed upon the ſeverall Counties for enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment of that Army, as yet come in to the Committee of <hi>Gold-Smiths</hi> Hall, for repayment of the months pay advanced by the City of <hi>London,</hi> and for ſatisfying the neceſſities of that Army, which is reduced to that extremity in the preſent ſervice wherein they are ingaged, that without Peaſe, Apples and greene Wheat, they gather from the ground, they are not able to ſubſiſt; ſome of the Counties, as <hi>Lincolne</hi> and <hi>Rutland,</hi> deſire to be excuſed, and pretend their inability to afford any proportion of the Money aſſeſſed upon them for that Army, and little or none comes in from the reſt of the Counties. It is above a twelve moneth ſince a moneths pay was ordered by the Houſe to be paid to the Scottiſh Army out of the Fines and Compoſitions for Delinquents Eſtates, immediatly after the Battell of <hi>Longmarſton,</hi> a good proportion whereof is yet due, the payment of which is obſtructed by ſeverall Orders procured from the Houſe, for payment of Moneys for other
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:113251:7"/> uſes, out of thoſe Fines and compoſitions. Our earneſt deſire to the honourable Houſe is, That ſome ſpeedy and effectuall courſe be taken for bringing in of the moneys due by the Counties for the foure Moneths paſt, that the Ordinance may ſpeedily be renewed; that the Houſe will be pleaſed to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point the Committee of <hi>Gold-Smiths</hi> Hall, firſt to pay the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder of that moneths Pay, voted after the Battell of <hi>Long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marſton,</hi> out of the Fines and Compoſitions for Delinquents Eſtates, notwithſtanding any ſubſequent Orders, and that the Committee of <hi>Gold-Smiths</hi> Hall may be enabled for the ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy payment thereof, and other incident charges, that the Houſe would call for their reports concerning thoſe Fines, wherein they can proceed no further without the approbation of the Houſes.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>7 <hi>Auguſt,</hi> 1645.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>By command of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners for the Parliament of</hi> Scotland. Joh. Cheiſley.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <p>HAving received from your Lordſhips ſome Votes of the honourable Houſes concerning the Propoſitions of Peace, and after ſome conference thereupon, being deſired by your Lordſhips to give our anſwer in writing, we hereby pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent our thoughts, and offer it to your Lorſhips conſideration, whether it were not fit to ſhun all occaſions of delay, in ſending the Propoſitions of Peace to the King, leaſt thereby we neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect the improvement of ſo ſeaſonable an opportunity of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining Peace, as we have expreſſed in our former papers: That to this end we are moſt ready, preſently to concurre with the honourable Houſes, for ſending to his Majeſty the Propoſitions, either all, or ſome, as they have been already agreed upon in the Parliaments of both Kingdomes, for mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and manner: That untill we underſtand what Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are intended by the Votes of the Houſes, to be next ſent,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:113251:8"/> we cannot give a cleare anſwer anent the manner. That if the Propoſitions preſented at <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>xbridge,</hi> be underſtood with any other of thoſe already agreed upon by both Kingdoms, which upon mutuall debate ſhall be adjudged moſt neceſſary for the Peace of both Kingdoms to be now ſent, we ſhall be ready to concurre with the Honourable Houſes to deſire a poſitive anſwer thereof from His Majeſtie without any Treaty.</p>
            <p>But in caſe any new Propoſitions of Peace be thereby un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, or any materiall additions to, or alterations of the former Propoſitions, we ſhall be neceſſitated to ſend theſe to the Kingdome of <hi>Scotland,</hi> to be there conſidered and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved, as all the fotmer were; and as it is evident that wee are not the cauſe of this delay, ſo that no prejudice may thereby ariſe to the publike, we deſire in the interim that thoſe already agreed upon by both Kingdoms (which at the time were thought ſufficient) may be preſented to His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie with all convenient ſpeed. Concerning the third Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve of the Houſes for preſenting their deſires by Bills to His Majeſty; If the meaning be to ſend the Propoſitions that are already agreed upon by the Parliaments of both Kingdoms, &amp; ſeek the Kings Majeſties poſitive anſwer thereunto; and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether therewith to preſent Bills conforme to thoſe Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions, for the more legall ſecuring of this Kingdome in the Kings grant of theſe Propoſitions, although we think it more ſafe and convenient for both Kingdoms, that the ſecurity of both ſhould proceed hand in hand, and <hi>ſimul &amp; ſemel,</hi> be perfected and conſummated, yet if the Honourable Houſes ſhall inſiſt upon the ſending ſuch Bills with the Propoſitions, we are ſo farre from giving any occaſion of delay (for which we are by ſome unjuſtly blamed) that we will be ready to concurre, the Kingdom of <hi>England</hi> ſecuring us, as they did in the large Treaty, both in relation to the King, and in relation
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:113251:8"/> to themſelves, as we are bound to doe the like to them. And withall we deſire, that if theſe Bills be not ready, the ſending of the Propoſitions be not delayed, the grant whereof by his Majeſty will be an ingagement, and make way for his aſſent to the Bills. But if the meaning be to ſend Bills without ſending the Propoſitions agreed upon by both Parliaments, or with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out deſiring the Kings Anſwer thereunto, then we ſhall be neceſſitated to know the pleaſure of the Parliament of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> concerning this new way before we can joyne in it, and in the meane time deſire the Honourable Houſes to take into their ſerious conſideration, that the former way agreed upon by both Kingdoms is laid aſide, and that this new way of ſending Bills without Propoſitions was not thought neceſſary in any former addreſſe to his Majeſty for peace. Neither was it propoſed to us, or communicated to the Parliament of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> which is now adjourned, ſo that we cannot communicate the ſame unto them for the preſent. That it is not in the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of any Commiſſioner from a Parliament to forme the Propoſitions in Bills, or Acts of Parliament, and to deſire the Kings ratification thereof, before ſuch Bills or Acts be known and agreed upon by the Parliament it ſelfe; that the way of the Propoſitions as they are conceived by both Parliaments is a joynt way, uniting the Kingdoms in their deſires, tying the King to both in his Grants, and obleiging both to ſee theſe performed and preſerved, each in favour of the other, and ſo doth double the ſecurity, as both by way of Law, and way of Covenant, and agravates the violation of any Article, as the violation of both Law and Covenant, whereas the way of Bills without the Propoſitions is a more dividing way, both of the deſires of the Kingdoms, of the Kings Anſwers thereunto, and of their Obligations to ſee the ſame performed; and therefore a disjunctive way was moſt earneſtly preſſed by the Kings Commiſſioners at <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>xbridge,</hi> as moſt conducible to
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:113251:9"/> their ends, and pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>diciall to ours, and for that cauſe was op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by the Commiſſioners of both Kingdoms.</p>
            <p>That ſeeing the Parliament of <hi>Scotland</hi> is not preſently ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd did not know of this way, and that we cannot have pow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r to form Acts of Parliament, this were to propoſe, and deſire the ſetling the peace of the one kingdome without ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the other; which as it were contrary to the Covenant, and the Treaty, ſo would it be made uſe of by our common adverſaries, to be the occaſion of ruining the peace of both; and therefore we rather deſire that the way already agreed upon by both Kingdoms may be obſerved, as that which will occaſion both leaſt delay, and leſſe danger, eſpecially ſeeing we are willing to crave a poſitive anſwer to the Propoſitions without any Treaty: And for the way of ſecurity, we deſire that the way ſo ſolidly agreed upon by both Kingdoms for eſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bliſhing of the large Treaty, and inſerted in the beginning and cloſe of the Acts of Parliament of both Kingdoms in the yeare of God 1641. may be ſeriouſly conſidered, as contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning a three-fold ſecurity, the one of ingroſſing all the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, and paſſing them by way of a Law, and Act of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament; the other by way of the Kings Covenant, and Oath to his people; the third, by the Parliaments of both King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms; giving their full aſſurance, and making Publick Faith in name of both Kingdoms reſpectively for the true and faithfull obſervance thereof; all which upon the Kings grant of the Propoſitions may be ſpeedily diſpatched; and ſecurely ſetled, which is our chiefeſt deſire for the good of both Kingdoms.</p>
            <p>And it were earneſtly to be wiſhed in a matter of ſo tender a nature as the buſineſſe of peace, wherein the mutuall adviſe and c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nſent of both Kingdoms is neceſſarily required, that neither Kingdom ſhould engage themſelves without a previ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous debate, eſpecially in alteration of any thing formerly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed on.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>14. <hi>Aug.</hi> 1645.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>By command of the Scottiſh Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners for the Parliament of</hi> Scotland. Joh. Cheiſley.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:113251:9"/>
            <p>UPon ſeverall occaſions we have repreſented to the Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of Parliament the extream wants and neceſſities of the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Army, and particularly of late in a paper of the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> to which we have received no anſwer.</p>
            <p>It is fourteene moneths ſince a moneths pay was ordered by the Houſe of Commons to be payed to the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Army out of the Fines, and compoſitions for delinquents Eſtates, imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly after the battle of <hi>Long-marſton,</hi> a great proportion whereof remaines yet due, and cannot be paid by reaſon ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Orders are procured from the Houſe in prejudice thereof, for payment of monies for other uſes out of thoſe Fines and compoſitions. It is about ſeaven moneths ſince the Houſe of Parliament did paſſe an Ordinance aſſeſſing the ſeverall Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties towards the entertainment of that Army, of all which there is only come in to the Committee of Goldſmiths Hall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout ſeaven or eight thouſand pounds, for repayment of the moneths pay advanced by the City of <hi>London,</hi> which is all that Army received for theſe ſeaven moneths paſt; and for the moneths pay Ordered by the Houſe upon the fifteenth of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> to be forthwith provided and furniſhed, there is no appearance of the providing thereof till the Houſe give fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther order.</p>
            <p>The Houſes of Parliament were alſo pleaſed to appoint two hundred pound <hi>per diem</hi> to be payed toward the maintenance of the Infantry of that Army, which though it hath been aſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the Commiſſioners of Parliament, yet hath proved very in effectuall, as the Commiſſioners themſelves have certified to the Houſe of Commons. We doe therefore againe renew our former requeſt to the Houſes, that they would be pleaſed to call for the Reports of the Committee of Goldſmiths Hall concerning thoſe Fines, and compoſitions, to enable them for
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:113251:10"/> ſpeedy payment of the remainder of that moneths pay Voted immediatly after the battle of <hi>Long-marſton,</hi> and to order no monies to be payed by that Committee out of thoſe Fines and compoſitions, till it ſhall be paid. That the months pay Orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the Houſe upon the fifteenth of <hi>Auguſt</hi> to be forthwith provided and ſent to the Army, may be accordingly furniſhed; and that a more effectuall courſe be taken for bringing in the monies aſſeſſed upon the ſeverall Counties for entertainment of that Army.</p>
            <p>We are informed that the Houſes of Parliament have now in conſideration the ſale of the delinquents Eſtates, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore have thought fit to put the Honourable Houſes in mind of the fifth Article of the Treaty between the Kingdoms, wherein it is provided, that the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Army ſhall be payed by the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> out of the Eſtates of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, Prelats, Malignants, and their adherents, or otherwiſe; and ſince it is cleerly evident, that all other waies for the maintenance of that Army have failed, we deſire that a ſtock of credit and ſecurity may be ſetled by Ordinance of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment out of the Lands and Eſtates of delinquents, for pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of what is due to the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Army, and that the Lands and Eſtates of delinquents be ingaged for no other uſe, till that Army receive ſatisfaction, which is now moſt neceſſary in regard of the great diſtractions of the Kingdom of <hi>Scotland;</hi> and we hope the Houſes of Parliament will be the more ready to ſupply them, that the only quarrell the enemy doth pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend againſt that Kingdom is, the aſſiſtance given by them to the Parliament of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>4th. September, 1645.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>By Command of the Commiſſioners for the Parliament of</hi> Scotland. John Cheiſly.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:113251:10"/>
            <p>IT hath pleaſed the Lord our God, who worketh all things according to the counſell of his owne Will, in his wiſe and and righteous Providence ſo to diſpoſe at this time, upon the affaires of the Kingdome of <hi>Scotland;</hi> that they are upon the ſudden brought to a more deplorable condition then could in any probability have been expected, or the enemy himſelfe in his pride could have preſumed.</p>
            <p>We ſpeake not of the devouring Peſtilence, which in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny parts of the Land, eſpecially in and about the chiefeſt City, hath raged for a long time, in many degrees above any thing that either our ſelves or our Predeceſſors have ever knowne, and hath taken away many thouſands of the people, nor is it yet ſtayed: This (although it hath been a great ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage to the enemy, and no ſmall diſcouragement and hinderance to the oppoſing of his power) we acknowledge to be a Plague from the more immediate hand of God, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt which there is no remedy from man, but the fervent prayers of the people of God, which we earneſtly deſire may be here continued, as they are piouſly begun, till the Lord be entreated for the Land.</p>
            <p>Our deſire is to repreſent what the ſword of the enemy hath done, after many conflicts in divers places of the North of the Kingdome, whereby great numbers have fallen, and the enemy, deſpicable in the beginning, had encreaſed in ſtrength and boldneſſe; at laſt, in the very bowels of the Kingdome: He hath ſo farre prevailed, that not onely thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of the beſt affected have loſt their lives, and divers of them taken priſoners, but alſo our whole Army and Forces are put to the worſt and ſcattered. Such as were moſt zealous of the Covenant and Cauſe of God (having no Armies on foot to joyne with, nor Garriſoned Townes for places of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:113251:11"/> refuge) are forced to fly for their lives, and to leave their ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitations, poſſeſſions, and all that they have in the world to the cruelty and ſpoile of the enemy. Many of the common ſort are drawne away by his flatteries and promiſes, by the Proclamations which he maketh, and the Declarations which he emitteth at his pleaſure, offering to them Protections to their perſons and eſtates, freedome and exemption from all the Taxes, Impoſitions, and burdnings, which they are preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with for the maintenance and ſupply of their Armies in <hi>England, Jreland,</hi> and at home in their owne Country; toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the liberty of their Religion according to their Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall Covenant, and all other liberties and priviledges for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly eſtabliſhed with his Majeſties conſent, upon condition that they will renounce their Covenant with <hi>England,</hi> and take an Oath that they ſhall no more lift Armes againſt the King and His aſſiſtants. Some of place and power, who for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly were either profeſſed enemies to Religion, or never tooke Religion to heart, have dealt falſly in the Covenant, and preſuming upon the ſucceſſe of the enemy, and waiting for ſuch a time as this is, have joyned with him againſt their Country. The moſt faithfull of the Miniſtery, by the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall enemy, and by Malignants in their owne Congregations, are driven from their ſtations, and forced to ſeeke ſhelter for the ſaving of their lives, whereby the people left behind are laid open to all ſorts of tentations, and Religion it ſelfe is in no ſmall danger. As we are not willing to conceale or extenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate their miſery, in this day of the Lords viſitation, ſo are we not able ſufficiently to expreſſe them; the yoake of their tranſgreſſions is bound by his hand, they are wreathed and come up upon their neck, he hath made their ſtrength to fall, the Lord hath delivered them into their hands, from whom they are not able to riſe up.</p>
            <p>In this their extreamity, the Committee of the Eſtates of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:113251:11"/> the Kingdom, being for the preſent put out of all hope of any ſucceſſe from the Forces in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and knowing no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther meanes of help, found it neceſſary, unleſſe they would loſe the Kingdom, and lie ſtill under ſuch miſeries as are more intollerable then death; That the Scottiſh Army in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> ſhould march Northward, to the end, that (if God in the meane time did provide no other way) they might come to their deliverance, and withall to implore the affection, counſell, and aſſiſtance of their Brethren in <hi>England;</hi> and therefore to ſend the Lord Chancellor for repreſenting their diſtreſſes and deſires to the Honourable Houſes.</p>
            <p>Concerning the ſpeedy march of the Scottiſh Army Northward for their reliefe, they ſuppoſed that Charity would move the Honourable Houſes and all charitable Chriſtians to conſider, that in time of extreme trouble, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall affection on both ſides, in calling for and in giving of help is unreſiſtable, and that there was no liberty left in ſuch a caſe, when both the publike, and every mans private were in hazard and well neere loſt, either for the Committee or for the Army, to conſult or to chuſe what to doe. That their Iuſtice would bring to their remembrance, that this Army (as is contained in the Treaty) was levied and came into <hi>England</hi> for the purſuance of the ends expreſſed in the Covenant, which were the ſafety of both Kingdomes, and their mutuall defence againſt the Popiſh, Prelaticall, and malignant party their adherents in both Kingdomes: and that they were to be employed where they were to be moſt uſefull for the common Cauſe, and for oppoſing the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my where his power and the danger was greateſt. In this notion was their marching to the North, when the King went Northward, looked upon. And now when his Forces have ſo farre prevailed in <hi>Scotland,</hi> their marching thither is to be interpreted to no other ſenſe. They ſuppoſed alſo that
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:113251:12"/> the wiſdome of the Honourable Houſes would make them ſee, that this expedition might, by the bleſſing of God, not only be a meane of deliverance to <hi>Scotland,</hi> but alſo prevent the invading of <hi>England</hi> by a new Army; which, if <hi>Scotland</hi> bee altogether ſubdued, may certainly be expected. The timous prevention of ſuch an Invaſion may prove no leſſe ſerviceable for the good of the cauſe, and of the Kingdome of <hi>England,</hi> then the preſent oppoſition of any hoſtile Army within the Kingdome of <hi>England.</hi> As theſe neceſſary con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations have moved the Committee of the Eſtates of <hi>Scotland</hi> to deſire the marching of their Army Northward, ſo are they confident, that the Honourable Houſes will reſt ſatisfied therewith. And doe expect from them, and from all the well-affected in <hi>England,</hi> a brotherly compaſſion, and Chriſtian fellow-feeling in their bitter ſufferings, all ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary aſſiſtance and ſeaſonable ſupply of Armes, Ammuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and money, and in due time ſuch Forces as may be ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, as through the encreaſe of their troubles their need ſhall call for and require them. It ſhall not be neceſſary to multiply arguments to this purpoſe: the wiſdome of the Parliament can call to remembrance the expreſſions in their owne Declaration of the 7 of <hi>November</hi> 1642, and in the Papers delivered in by their Commiſſioners in their names to the Convention of Eſtates in <hi>Scotland, Auguſt</hi> 12. 1643. Together with the Treaty and the ſolemne League and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant. It will never be forgotten by our Brethren of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> that when our Countrey was in great quietneſſe, and the greateſt aſſurance that was poſſible was offered for our fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſecurity, wee chooſed, rather then to enjoy our owne peace without the peace of this Kingdome, upon the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons contained in the Declaration of the Kingdome of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> to come with an Army into <hi>England</hi> againſt all diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragements that might ariſe, either from the ſtormy win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:113251:12"/> ſeaſon, or the power of a mighty Army in the North of this Kingdome ready to encounter us. What the endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, the actions, and the ſucceſſe of that Army were, let the Enemy before that time prevalent, from his owne ſenſe give teſtimony. When the Kingdome of <hi>Scotland</hi> had laid forth their ſtrength for the recovery of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of <hi>England,</hi> and promiſed to themſelves ſecurity from forraigne invaſion, eſpecially from <hi>Ireland,</hi> upon grounds contained in the large Treaty, and in the Propoſitions made by Commiſſioners ſent from both Houſes, and particularly by the Ships, which according to an Article of the late Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, were to be employed for defence of the Coaſt of <hi>Scotland;</hi> An Enemy nevertheleſſe from <hi>Ireland</hi> entred the Kingdome of <hi>Scotland,</hi> having no other controverſie, nor pretending any other cauſe againſt them, but their Treaty and Covenant with <hi>England,</hi> and their aſſiſtance following thereupon, and hath prevailed ſo farre, as hath made this ſad Remonſtrance neceſſary at this time.</p>
            <p>It is no matter of great difficulty (unleſſe wee will ſhut our eyes, and hide from our ſelves our owne danger and threatned ruine) to diſcerne and determine what is the great and maine deſigne of the Enemy, now waxed proud and inſolent by the afflictions which the Lord hath brought upon the Kingdome of <hi>Scotland:</hi> When hee hath brought all there under his power, a work, which through the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignancy of ſome open, and many formerly ſecret enemies, now appearing and joyning with him, through the ſufferings, calamities, and hatred brought upon the beſt affected, and ſuch as have beene moſt active and inſtrumentall in this Cauſe, and through the diſcontent and diſtemper of the multitude for the loſſe of their meanes and friends in this warre at home and abroad, he preſageth to be more eaſie and faeſceable, then what he hath already brought to paſſe. His ſecond expedition is againſt the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:113251:13"/> which is not any uncertaine conjecture, but his owne pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed reſolution and confidence; And is too apparent, that unleſſe he be ſpeedily ſuppreſſed, he may through the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe and combination of the Malignants of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and of the Northerne Counties of <hi>England,</hi> grow to a greater ſtrength, eſpecially if he joyne with the King and his Forces, which he is alſo very confident of, then be afterward eaſily oppoſed, and thereby may reduce theſe Kingdoms to a more miſerable condition, in reſpect both of Religion and Liberty (beſide all their intervening ſufferings) then they were in before the begining of this unhappy warre.</p>
            <p>We know the cauſe is the ſame which it was at the firſt undertaking, that the Godly in <hi>Scotland</hi> who loved it from the beginning, and are reſolved to live and die in it; that the conjunction of the two Kingdomes which the enemy labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth to divide, and ſo to overcome, is no leſſe beneficiall to both, then it was formerly conceived to be; That the Popiſh and prelaticall faction in forraine parts as well as His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Dominions, upon the union of theſe Kingdomes, are more ſtrictly and powerfully combined then they have beene at other times; That the Reformation of Religion, the common intereſt of all the reformed Churches in Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, groaning ſo long under the croſſe is as much to be looked unto as ever, and who knoweth but the Lord in his wiſdome and juſtice is putting both their Kingdomes to a further tryall, the one by ſuffering the other by doing that it may be known, whether they have been ſeeking their owne peace and preſervation, or the honour of his name, and the good of Religion. We may without giving the leaſt cauſe of offence in this conjuncture of time make uſe of the words of the Declaration of the Convention of Eſtates of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>Scotland</hi> to the ſubjects there, concerning their expedition into <hi>England,</hi> for the aſſiſtance of their Brethren only changing the perſons, and if they were not extant in
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:113251:13"/> that Declaration we would have expeſſed our ſelves in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther manner: The Lord ſave you from the curſe of <hi>Meroz,</hi> who came not to helpe the Lord, to helpe the Lord againſt the mighty, when we looke upon the cauſe which <hi>Scotland</hi> maintaineth, the Prayers, Teares and Blood which they have powred forth, and the inſolencies and blaſphemies of the Enemy, we cannot doubt but enlargement and deliverance ſhall come unto <hi>Scotland,</hi> but <hi>England</hi> hath reaſon to feare, if upon ſo faire a call they ſit ſtill, and hold their peace, they ſhall periſh by the hand of the ſame enemy, and there ſhall be none to deliver them. We have many grounds of aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance that this cloud ſhall paſſe over, and after the Lord has proved and tryed the conſtancy of his ſervants, the malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancy of hipocrites, and the fellow feeling of our Brethren, his face will againe ſhine upon us, and his hand will raiſe us up and ruine our enemies; Our deſire and expectation is that in the day of our rejoycing, our Brethren may rejoyce with us and be comforted in this teſtimony, that they did not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake us in the day of trouble.</p>
            <p>Wee cannot deny that during the ſitting of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and divers times before, this Kingdome hath laid to heart the dangers of the Kingdome of <hi>Scotland,</hi> nor can it be denied that the Kingdome of <hi>Scotland</hi> hath of late given a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundant teſtimony of their affection and faithfulneſſe to this Kingdome, in departing the Kingdome in ſuch a manner, in the yeare 1641. which wee mention becauſe of the many ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter ſuſpitions and unjuſt calumnies vented to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and by their comming againe to this Kingdome at ſuch a time, for ſuch ends, and againſt ſo many impediments.</p>
            <p>If any diſcontents, differences or jealoſies have beene raiſed, which were nothing ſtrange, becauſe very ordinary and incident in time of War, a time that uſeth to produce ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and great difficulties, wee deſire they may be all mutuall forgiven and forgotten, that the War be managed in <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:113251:14"/> as in <hi>England</hi> by the joynt counſells of both Kingdomes, and that in every thing a right underſtanding, and a ſtrong mutuall confidence may be revived and renewed, that either Kingdome may helpe the other in time of trouble, as if they were but one Kingdome, and that the Lord may delight to bleſſe the endeavours of both.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Sep.</hi> 1645.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>By command of the Committee for the Parliament of <hi>Scotland.</hi> IOHN CHEISLEY.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <p>VVHereas in anſwer to our paper of the date <hi>Iune</hi> 20. 1645. bearing our earneſt deſires of the ſetling of Religion and Peace in theſe Kingdomes, and our other papers ſince to the ſame effect, diverſe votes of the Lords and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons in Parliament aſſembled, have beene communicated unto us, which for ſo long a time have not been effectuall to produce the intended, and ſo much deſired ends. We are up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on many and very urgent cauſes, conſtrained to renew our former deſires, and are very confident, that the honourable houſes judging of us in relation to the truſt committed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us, as if wee were their own Commiſſioners in the like caſe, And conſider that our demands of eſtabliſhing Truth &amp; Peace, are not only agreeable unto, but confident with their own maine intentions, for which they have done and endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſo much; We ſhall not onely be free of the cenſure of importunity; but ſhall have their approbation, with ſuch an anſwer as may give us ſatisfaction, and put our minds to reſt hereafter.</p>
            <p>And firſt concerning Religion, we bleſſe God and thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully acknowledge the zeale and endeavours of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, for what is already done in the matter of the Directo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for the publike worſhip of God; But cannot wonder e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough what ſhould be the cauſe that the government of the Church, which is the wall of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and the hedge for preſerving of other parts of Religion, is ſo long expected by all the Reformed Churches, eſpecially by the Church of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:113251:14"/> 
               <hi>Scotland,</hi> ſo earneſtly deſired by the Aſſembly, by the godly of the Miniſtry and people both in City and Countrey, is op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by the enemy as the finall determination of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies of Religion, and the ruine of all their preſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and expectation ever to recover themſelves, and would ſo much conduce for Order and Peace both in Church and State; ſhould ſtay ſo long in the birth, and not be brought forth and eſtabliſhed.</p>
            <p>We cannot conceive the want of the love of Religion which is ſo acceptable to God, that without it nothing can be accepted, and ſo profitable both to the publick and to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very mans private, that it is the one thing that is neceſſary, to be the cauſe; when wee remember that the honourable Houſes by their Commiſſioners, and in their Declarations to the Kirk and Kingdome of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and the reverend Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly of Divines in their letters by their direction, have ſo fully and frequently profeſſed, That Religion was the controverſie betwixt them and the contrary party, And the chief ground of craving aid and aſſiſtance from the Kingdome of <hi>Scotland,</hi> And of the ſolemne League and Covenant, now known to all the World, the prime Articles whereof, are for the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of Religion as well in diſcipline and government, as in doctrine and worſhip, and for unity and uniformity in all theſe, in the three kingdomes. Like as upon the other part, it was the principall cauſe that moved the Kingdome of <hi>Scotland,</hi> to deny themſelves, to forſake their own peace and eaſe, and to joyne with their Brethren in the time of their diſtreſſe, for proſecuting this war, wherein they have ſpent ſo much bloud in this Kingdome and at home, loſt ſo many worthy and pretious men and endured ſo many miſeries; In all which and againſt death it ſelfe, their chiefeſt comfort hath been the teſtimony of their conſciences, that they were contending, ſuffering, and dying for Religion, And for the Cauſe and Covenant of God, which is alſo the conſolation
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:113251:15"/> of their Widdowes, Orphanes and Friends, whom they have left behind them.</p>
            <p>Nor do we apprehend how the judgement or obſtruction doth come from any other party: Such as have wilfully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed to joyn themſelves in Covenant, or do deale falſely in the Covenant, are not to be regarded, but are to be reckoned amongſt the enemies, And what ever their profeſſions or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences be, are not indeed ſerving the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, or the publick, but ſeeking themſelves and their own ends, And ſuch as have taken the Covenant, and make conſcience of the Oath of God, will not ſleight Reformation, Vniformity, or the extirpation of ſuperſtition, hereſy, ſchiſme, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fanneſſe, far leſſe appeare againſt the ſetling of the govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Church, But will with all their ſtrength endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour it, as the meane appointed of God for ſo neceſſary ends; No man can be ſo deſtitute of ſenſe and reaſon, as to thinke ſuch an Anarchy and confuſion as now prevaileth in the Churches of this Kingdome, to be the Ordinance of God; No Chriſtian can be ſo void of knowledge and faith, as to imagine ſuch a monſtrous deformity, to be the beauty and glory of the Kingdome of Chriſt on earth; No brother can beare a mind ſo contrary to charity, as to judge ſuch an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolerable condition, to be the reward of ſo much bloud as hath beene ſhed in this cauſe, And of the ſo many and gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious ſufferings of all the three Kingdomes; Nay wee are perſwaded that God hath provided better things for us, that neceſſity will bring all that tender the preſervation of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the peace of the Church, to joyn at laſt in the right order, and government of the Church, and that both Houſes (which is all our deſire, concerning this) will adde from that authority, wherewith God hath veſted them, their civill Sanction, to what the pious and learned Aſſembly after long and ſerious debates, have adviſed as moſt agreeable to the Word of God.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:113251:15"/>
            <p>There be alwaies ſome Incendiaries and evill inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments who will be raiſing jealouſies againſt Church-government, as a collaterall power erecting it ſelfe at the ſide of the Civill, and in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd overtopping it, which is nothing elſe but to raiſe jealouſies againſt the ſpirituall Kingdome of Chriſt, as if it were inconſiſtent with the Kingdome of this World. In other places where Civill powers are no leſſe tender to their greatneſſe and ſuperio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, there is no ſuch thing. Upon the contrary, the Civill powers finde their honour and authoritie increaſed, the people under them more dutifull and obedient, and their places more comfortable both in peace and war, by the Diſcipline of the Church in Presbyteries and Synods. Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters in their perſons and profeſſions are ſubject to Civill authority, and though they receive the rules and directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of their Miniſterie from Chriſt, yet may the Civill power command and compell them to doe their duty in preaching, adminiſtring the Sacraments, and exerciſing of Diſcipline, and may hold them to ſuch principles as are well knowne by the confeſſions of the Reformed Churches, and their long peaceable practice agreeable thereunto: And therefore no danger is to be feared from their power, but much helpe and happineſſe from their faithfulneſſe, if they finde encouragement from the Civill power, which they will greatly need againſt ſo many diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties as they have to wreſtle with before this Church be ſetled in purity and peace.</p>
            <p>It is no mervaile that wicked men the ſonnes of <hi>Belial</hi> are unwilling to ſubmit their necks to this yoke that Chriſt may raigne over them; this is their corruption and will prove their miſery. But it is the excellencie and praiſe of Church-government, that it is terrible to ſuch as an Army with banners. Nor ſhould it ſeem ſtrange that ſome of the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:113251:16"/> godly, who have been ſore preſſed with Prelaticall tyranny and uſurpation, ſhould be afraid of all Eccleſiaſticall go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment. But this will appeare to be needleſſe feare, when they caſt their eyes upon the ſweet and peaceable govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of all the reformed Churches for ſo many yeeres; and when they conſider that the power of the Keyes is not to be exerciſed at the pleaſure of any one in a Monarchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call way, but by a Company and Colledge of Miniſters and Elders, choſen with the conſent of the people: Or that others of the godly meaſuring the conſtitution of Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries and Aſſemblies by the corruption and prophaneneſſe of many Presbyters in the Prelaticall times, ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive of them as formidable to the power of godlineſſe; But when they ſhall perceive that by the wiſdome and care of the Parliament, the Presbyters and Aſſemblies are conſtituted and made up of orthodox, pious, and ſelect perſons, zealous of the honour of Jeſus Chriſt, and of the edification of ſoules, this feare will vaniſh. Nor can there be any other remedy of ſo many feares and jelouſies, but the ſetting up of the government it ſelfe, which by the power of God accompanying his owne Ordinance, will prove a comfort to the godly, a meanes to winne many to Chriſt, and a matter of rejoycing to all who have been in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments of ſo good a worke, eſpecially to the honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable houſes of Parliament, whom we therefore earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſire, againſt all obloquies and impediments, by their authority to eſtabliſh it, that it may in reality ſpeake for it ſelfe above any verball expreſſions of ours; and when we ſee Religion ſo far promoted, we may the more cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully proceed in the common cauſe, as knowing that wee have not been beating the ayre.</p>
            <p>Our other renewed deſire is concerning peace, which of all things, next to truth, is moſt deſireable; for attaining
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:113251:16"/> whereof, we conceive two things to be neceſſary: One is, that ſeeing by Gods good providence, the Scottiſh Army is not yet neceſſitated to goe for Scotland, but may remain in this Kingdome, a ſolid courſe may be taken, according to the Treaty for their neceſſary maintenance, that they be encouraged to act their part, and be kept from ſuch o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther waies, as have been, and muſt be uncomfortable to themſelves, and hurtfull to their brethren here, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon much diſcontent ariſeth on both ſides, and by joynt counſels may be directed and ſet in ſuch a way for proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting of the warre, as may be moſt effectuall and benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall for this, and conſequently of both Kingdomes.</p>
            <p>The other thing which wee conceive to be neceſſary is, that Propoſitions of peace be ſpeedily diſpatcht to His Majeſty. This wee have preſſed divers times before, and have waited for the reſults of the conſideration of the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe by the houſe of Commons, conforme to their Order of the 18 of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> but till this time wee have not heard what progreſſe they have made. Our opportunity herein is not greater then our Commiſſion is urgent, and our Commandements frequent, to take all occaſions for ſpeed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſetlement of truth and peace, the ends which have engaged us to this warre. Of late when our Kingdome in the wonderfull providence of God was brought low, wee were altogether ſilent, leſt our deſire ſhould have appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to proceed rather from impatience under the ſence of our ſufferings, then from our ſincerity and zeale of the publique peace; But now when the mighty hand of God hath wrought a notable deliverance for Scotland, and hath bleſſed the Armies of this Kingdome with marvellous ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, by which meanes the King having no conſiderable ſtrength to relie upon in Scotland or England, may be humbled, and his heart prepared for hearkening to peace,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:113251:17"/> wee conceive the motion to be more ſeaſonable, and doe hope it will be more ſucceſſefull then ever before, and what the Lord will doe hereafter when opportunities have not been taken hold of, wee doe not know, nor is it for us to conjecture: but ſo much wee may in certainty foreſee, that if the King ſhall grant ſuch Propoſitions as may be the foundation of a ſafe and firme peace, wee have that which ought to be the common deſire of all the three Kingdomes in the moſt eaſie way. And if (which God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid) his heart ſhall be ſtill averſe, our advantage is great, having beſides the approbation of God, and the eternall peace of our owne ſoules, the teſtimony of the world and the conviction of our enemies, together with the ſtronger reſolution, when we are at out wits end to follow the war, and thereby within a ſhort time (through the bleſſing of God) to obtaine our peace.</p>
            <p>Concerning the Kingdome of Scotland, the reports of others, and their owne ſpeculations of the miſeries of war in forraine parts, are felt of them, and verified of late in their lamentable experience; as the want of ordinary Courts, and courſes of juſtice; the decay of commerce and trade by Sea and Land, to the impoveriſhing of the Kingdome, and making of thouſands of families to beg, who hardly can finde ſupply from the richer ſort, becauſe their revenues are not payd them; the plunder and deva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation of the Souldiers; the aſſeſments, preſſures, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neceſſary burdens laid upon the Subjects for intertaining the warre, above that which they are able to beare; the great effuſion of blood, and the cutting off of many of the beſt affected, with other ſufferings of women and children, which are grievous to remember. And when by the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities of a long laſting warre, they are brought low and exhauſted of men and meanes, the danger of drawing in
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:113251:17"/> the barbarous Iriſh, or ſome other forraine enemy to their utter undoing: The difficulties and diſtreſſes of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome through the long continuance of this unnaturall warre, are better knowne to the wiſdome of the honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Houſes, then to us: Yet after ſo long reſidence upon publique imployments in this place, we cannot be ſo voyd of the knowledge and ſenſe of them, as not to apprehend the danger of the like extremity at laſt, unto our brethren of England.</p>
            <p>Seeing therefore the Fields are now white to the Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt both of perfecting the Reformation of Religion, and of making a ſure and well-grounded Peace, and there be ſo ſtrong inclinations and deſires, ſo many invitations and encouragements, ſo fit preparations, and ſutable diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions on all hands for ſo bleſſed a worke, wee doe in all earneſtneſſe deſire, that the opportunity which can hardly be redeemed when once loſt, may be improved to the greateſt advantage by the wiſdome and zeale of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Houſes, and doe expect their ſpeedy anſwer, that wee may be able to render an account to the Parliament of Scotland, or to thoſe that ſent us, and waite for it at our hands.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>By command of the Commiſſioners of the Parliament of Scotland,</hi> JOHN CHEISLEY.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>September,</hi> 1645.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <p>UPon the 26. of this inſtant your Lordſhips did com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate to us the reſolutions of both Houſes, to which you deſired a ſpeedy anſwer, and further acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted us, that the Papers by us lately given in were under conſideration of the houſe, and that wee ſhall receive their anſwer with all conveniency; and upon the 27 your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips renewed the ſame deſires.</p>
            <p>Wee cannot give a poſitive anſwer to the deſire of both
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:113251:18"/> Houſes concerning the diſpoſall of the Army becauſe it is not in our power, but we ſhall communicate their deſires forthwith to the Committee with the Army, and preſſe them with all the earneſtneſſe we can, to which we expect they will be ready to give all juſt ſatisfaction, ſo farre as the ſeaſon of the yeere may admit; and in the meane time wee deſire a ſpeedy anſwer to our Paper of the fourth of this inſtant, and the other of the twelfth, ſo farre as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes Money, Armes, and Ammunition, which is ſtill as neceſſary for accompliſhment of our deſires, as if the Army had marched into Scotland, and the ſpeedie proceeding thereof will be a great encouragement to that Army, and furtherance to their undertakings.</p>
            <p>It is well enough knowne to the honourable Houſes, how farre that Armie hath been diſappointed of provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions formerly, (having, for inſtance, received but one moneths pay theſe ſeven moneths paſt) how much their proceedings have been retarded this Summer, and ſome of their undertakings fruſtrate for want of neceſſary ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodation. And we deſire it may be conſidered, what hinderance it may be to the publique ſervice, if for the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture effectuall courſe ſhall not be taken for their entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and other neceſſaries.</p>
            <p>It is agreed upon by the Treaty that 31000 li. ſhould be monethly allowed, and payed towards the maintenance of that Armie, for reall performance whereof, many De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations have been made by the honourable Houſes of Parliament, before and ſince the entrie of that Army into this Kingdome; and finding the monies ariſing out of the Aſſeſſments and Revenues of the Northerne Counties, were not ſufficient for maintenance thereof, did in <hi>February</hi> laſt paſſe an Ordinance of Parliament for aſſeſſing 21000 pound monethly upon the ſeverall Counties therein men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned: of all which (there being now full ſeven moneths
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:113251:18"/> paſt) there is onely come in to the Committee of Gold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmiths-hall about 12000 li. which together with 19000 li. yet to be brought in they are obliged to repay to the Citie of London, for the moneths pay by them advanced; ſo that there is no probability that any conſiderable propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion can for a long time be brought in to ſupply the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities of that Army, eſpecially there being two other aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſments which precede the aſſeſſments of the Scottiſh Army, (although the Treaty between the Kingdoms doth precede them all, and ought to be obſerved as ſoone as any particular Ordinance,) and theſe aſſeſſments for other Armies are really executed, and moneys thereupon col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected by the Counties and brought in: whereas the aſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for the Scottiſh Armie is almoſt wholly neglected, is not executed by others, and cannot be executed by us, our very demanding the queſtion being clamored againſt, as intermedling with their eſtates; Neither is it our deſire in the leaſt kind to intermeddle, providing that it were remembred that not a written Ordinance, but reall pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment can ſatisfie the neceſſities of the Souldiers.</p>
            <p>By the ſame Ordinance 20 <hi>February,</hi> 1644. the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners of Exciſe appointed by Ordinance of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or their reſpective Deputies and Commiſſioners are ordained to pay 3000 li. monethly out of the whole Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe ariſing out of the ſix Northerne Counties. And though the Excize is accounted, and doth really prove to all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, to be one of the beſt ſecurities within the Kingdome, yet all waies are taken to make it ineffectuall to that army, ſo that there hath not been one hundred pound thereof received in all, for theſe five moneths paſt, the profits thereof being almoſt wholly anticipated and fore-ſtalled here in the South, and applied to other uſes, and in all appearance ſhall ſtill continue in that condition, unleſſe the honourable Houſes give further order herein to the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:113251:19"/> Commiſſioners of Excize for paiment of that 3000 li. to the Scots Armie, according to the intent of the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance.</p>
            <p>Concerning the Coale of Newcaſtle, the price thereof hath been ſo much diminiſhed, and the trade thereby de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed, that this laſt moneth the profits thereof have not amounted to above eight hundred pounds, whereas they were eſtimated by your Lordſhips in a Paper of <hi>November</hi> 1644. to ſeven thouſand pound <hi>per menſem,</hi> for and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the paiment of the 31000 li. monethly due to the Scottiſh Armie.</p>
            <p>There was alſo 200 li. <hi>per diem</hi> lately appointed to be paid to the Infantrie of that Armie, whereof they never received one penny to this houre, as was certified to the houſe of Commons by their Commiſſioners, in their Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of <hi>Auguſt</hi> 31.</p>
            <p>The obſtructions and failings in the waies appointed by the Houſes for the entertainment of that Armie, with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers others, we have repreſented in our former Papers, to which wee have never received any anſwer, nor ſeen any effectuall courſe taken for redreſſe thereof. And if the Houſes ſhall be pleaſed to remove theſe obſtructions, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply the defects, and take an effectuall courſe for their en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment, the Scottiſh Armie will be very farre from giving the leaſt occaſion to the Parliament to make any Declaration more concerning them, nor other Armies within the Kingdome againſt laying of Taxes or raiſing of any contribution upon any Countie or part of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, or giving any cauſe of complaint to the Countrie. And we are perſwaded it is the earneſt deſire of that armie to evidence according to the ninth Article of the Treatie, that their enterance into, and continuance in England, ſhall be made uſe of to no other ends then are expreſſed in the Covenant and Treatie. But if no effectuall courſe ſhall
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:113251:19"/> be taken for their entertainment, according to the Treaty, and that it ſhall not be thought lawfull for them to provide for their neceſſary ſubſiſtence in the parts where they ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, we leave it to the Houſes of Parliament to judge whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it muſt not inevitably follow that they ſhall either ſtarve or disband, which we are confident is as farre from the inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Honourable Houſes, as it is againſt the Law of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, the cauſe wherein, and the Covenant and Treaty where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, that Army was ingaged.</p>
            <p>Theſe things out the conſcience of our duty and ſenſe of the truſt put upon us, we could not forbeare to expreſſe for our owne exoneration; nor doe we repreſent them to expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtulate for the time paſt; but that a ſpeedy and effectuall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy may be taken by the Honourable Houſes for the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, whereby that Army may be enabled and rendred more active in advancing the publike ſervice.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>29. <hi>Sept.</hi> 1645.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>By command of the Commiſſioners for the Kingdome of</hi> Scotland. John Cheiſley.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <p>TO give a more poſitive anſwer to the deſires of the Houſes concerning the marching of the Scottiſh Army to beſiege <hi>Newarke</hi> was not in our power, nor within the bounds of our Commiſſion: But what was in our power for ſatisfying the deſires of the Houſes, that we have done with all diligence; for we did forthwith communicate the deſires of the Houſes to the Committee of the Parliament of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> reſiding with the Army, and intruſted for their part with the power of diſpoſing of the Army, and with all ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtneſſe
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:113251:20"/> did preſſe a ſpeedy and ſatisfactory anſwer, which we doe ſhortly expect; becauſe by Letters which we have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by this Poſt, we underſtand there is a meeting of that Committee, and of ſome of the generall Officers of that Army upon the borders with the Committee of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and we are very hopefull the reſult of their conſultations ſhall tend to the bettering the condition of that Army, the advancing of the publike ſervice, and the ſatisfying the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires of both Houſes of Parliament.</p>
            <p>As it ſhall be our earneſt deſire and conſtant endeavours, That the Scottiſh Army may be active in the proſecuting the Warre untill the peace of both Kingdoms be ſetled, ſo we cannot but renue our deſires to the Honourable Houſes to take more to heart the neceſſities of that Army, the removall of the obſtructions, and ſupply of the defects of the wayes ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for their maintenance; and we earneſtly entreat for a ſpeedy anſwer to the particulars repreſented by us in our former Papers concerning the Army, and for ſetling of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and procuring the common Peace of both Kingdoms, which were the maine cauſes and ends that engaged us in this Warre.</p>
            <p>It may be equally conſidered by the Honourable Houſes, when now the Kingdome of <hi>Scotland,</hi> out of the earneſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire upon the grounds contained in the Covenant and Treaty to procure the peace of this Kingdome, have denied them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and loſt their owne peace, and are obliged by Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, Treaty, and joynt Declaration of both Kingdoms, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to lay downe Armes till the peace be ſetled. To what ſtraits the Kingdome of <hi>Scotland</hi> is brought, if the Houſes of Parliament, being earneſtly and frequently deſired by that Kingdome, ſhall delay to joyne in ſeeking a ſafe and well-grounded Peace upon termes already agreed upon by the joint conſent of both Kingdoms, and in the meane time ſhall
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:113251:20"/> not provide a ſure way of entertainment for the Scotch Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, and thereby enable them, according to the Treaty, to proſecute the Warre. When this is laid to heart by the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and brotherly affection of the Houſes of Parliament, we doe not doubt but in their juſtice and equity they will judge of our difficulties and deſires as if they were their own, and will determine and doe as in the like caſe they would expect from the Kingdom of <hi>Scotland.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>9. <hi>October</hi> 1645.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>By command of the Commiſſioners for the Parliament of</hi> Scotland. John Cheiſley.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
